Steam has new hardware out.
Steam 出新硬體了
It's a controller.
是個手柄
Costs $100.
賣 700 塊
Sold out everywhere within hours of release.
剛出幾個小時就全網斷貨
I got mine by staying up late
我這個也是我半夜
and frantically hitting refresh.
狂按刷新鍵搶到的
It's so expensive,
它這麼貴
yet so popular.
卻這麼火
Half of that is because Steam has always had a great reputation.
一半是因為 Steam 一直以來的口碑都很好
The other half is because
一半是因為
it's actually quite special.
它還真的挺特別的
If you're the target audience Gabe Newell has in mind,
如果你是 G 胖瞄準的目標用戶
it might even be
它甚至會是一個
the ultimate choice surpassing all other controllers.
超越所有其他手柄的終極選擇
So this video will tell you everything
所以這期視頻會完整地告訴你
you need to know about the Steam Controller.
關於 Steam Controller 你所需要知道的一切
All its features,
各種功能特性
and most importantly,
以及最重要的
whether it's worth buying.
它到底值不值得買
Looking at the design, the Steam Controller
看外觀 Steam 手柄
is a symmetrical full-featured PC controller.
是一個對稱佈局的全功能 PC 手柄
The joysticks are symmetrically placed.
搖杆位置左右對稱
Buttons are A, B, X, Y.
按鍵是 A B X Y
There are a few extra Steam-themed buttons.
額外有幾個 Steam 主題的按鍵
Four back buttons on the rear.
背後有 4 個背鍵
No 3.5mm headphone jack.
沒有 3.5 毫米耳機孔
Oh,
哦
what's that?
你說它是什麼
It's a screw hole.
它是一個螺絲孔
Clearly easy to disassemble.
一看就方便拆機
Unlike other PC controllers,
和其他 PC 手柄不一樣的是
these two trackpads inherited from the Steam Deck
這兩個繼承自 Steam Deck 的觸控板
are what make
也因為它倆
the Steam Controller's shape square and wide.
Steam 手柄外形整個很方很寬大
The joystick position
搖杆的位置
is pushed to a somewhat less reachable spot.
也被擠到了有點不那麼好夠的地方
Here's how it looks in the hands of our colleague with large hands.
這是我們 180 大手同事拿著的時候的樣子
It feels a bit tight,
會感覺有點極限
not very comfortable.
不那麼舒服了
But this hard-to-reach aspect
但是這個不好夠
for those with small hands who
對於本來手就小到
can't fully grip it anyway,
不太能夠完整握持住的人來說
is actually not that hard to accept.
其實沒那麼難接受
Honestly, I got used to it pretty quickly.
說實話我上手還挺習慣的
These joysticks are quite high-tech.
這一對搖杆還挺有科技含量的
They're called TMR joysticks.
它叫做 TMR 搖杆
You may have heard of
你可能聽說過
Hall effect joysticks that almost never drift.
幾乎不會漂移的霍爾搖杆
TMR is the next generation of Hall effect,
TMR 呢就是霍爾的下一代
more accurate and lower power consumption.
更準確功耗更低
And it hardly drifts at all.
而且也幾乎不會漂移
Probably because it's large.
可能是因為體積大
So it's heavier than a regular controller.
所以重量也比常規手柄要重一些
The upside is extremely long battery life.
好處是換來了超長的遊戲續航
The Steam Controller
Steam 手柄
can last about thirty-something hours.
大約是能夠持續玩三十幾個小時的
I feel like the PS5 controller barely lasts 6 hours.
我感覺 PS5 手柄差不多 6 小時就不行了
Overall, the feel is okay.
手感整體來說就是還可以
All buttons are membrane switches.
按鍵都是薄膜開關
The joysticks are very smooth.
搖杆很絲滑
But the back buttons are a bit easy to accidentally press.
就是背鍵稍微有點容易誤觸
Grip feel is better than the Steam Deck handheld.
握持感的話比掌機的 Steam Deck 要好一些
But still a bit worse than first-party controllers.
但是和第一方手柄比還是差了一點
Build quality too.
做工也是
Surface texture is also slightly lacking.
表面質感也差一點點
To be honest,
說實話
it's like a Steam Deck with the screen cut off.
它有點像從中間切掉了螢幕的 Steam Deck
Hehe.
嘿嘿
It's the opposite design philosophy of the PlayStation Portal.
和 PlayStation Portal 的設計思路正好相反
Next is compatibility.
然後是相容性
Steam's official statement is
Steam 官方的說法是
it only supports all operating systems that can install Steam.
只支持所有能安裝 Steam 的操作系統
That means it doesn't support PS5, Switch, or Xbox.
也就是說它不支持 PS5 Switch 和 Xbox
Nor iOS or Android.
也不支持 iOS 和安卓
But it supports Windows, macOS, and Linux.
但是支持 Windows macOS 和 Linux
Including SteamOS, of course.
當然也包括 SteamOS
This compatibility
這個相容性
actually reflects well
其實能夠很好地體現
the purpose of the Steam Controller.
Steam 手柄存在的意義
Most controllers are made for console games,
一般的手柄都是為了主機遊戲而生的
with PC compatibility as an afterthought.
順便相容一下 PC
But Steam wanted to make
而 Steam 希望做一個
a controller specifically for PC games.
專門為 PC 遊戲而生的手柄
So it needed things ordinary controllers don't have:
所以它還得有普通手柄沒有的東西
trackpads,
觸控板
paddles,
Puck
and the Steam Input software that ties it all together.
和連接起一切的 Steam Input 軟體
The trackpads,
觸控板
at first glance,
乍一看
seem similar to the Steam Deck's trackpads,
感覺和 SteamDeck 的觸控板差不多
just a nice bonus.
只是錦上添花
You might not use them much.
可能一共也用不上幾次
But on Windows,
但是在 windows 上
the trackpads are a lifesaver.
觸控板就是 雪中送炭了
The Steam Controller
Steam Controller
isn't actually the first controller Steam released.
其實不是 Steam 推出的第一個手柄
This one is.
它才是
The trackpads are much larger,
觸控板的占比要更大
even squeezing out the original d-pad and joystick.
甚至把原本的方向鍵 搖杆都擠沒了
Valve is so persistent about trackpads
Valve 之所以對觸控板這麼執著
because PC games
是因為 PC 遊戲
want to enter the living room,
想要進入客廳
connect to the TV,
接上電視
but without a keyboard and mouse to rely on,
但又沒有鍵鼠可以依賴
the controller must handle most operations.
那就必須要讓手柄完成大部分操作了
Then there's the Puck,
然後是 Puck
the small 2.4G receiver that comes with the Steam Controller.
就是 Steam 手柄自帶的小 2.4G 接收器
This thing is pucking amazing.
這個東西簡直 Pucking amazing
It also has magnetic charging functionality.
它同時有磁吸充電的功能
Input latency is much lower than Bluetooth.
輸入延遲比藍牙低不少
The signal is very good.
信號非常好
And one Puck can connect four controllers.
而且一個 Puck 可以連接四個手柄
Most importantly,
最重要的是
the Puck combined with the touchpad
Puck 配合觸控板
completely changes the interaction method for Windows games in the living room.
徹底改變了客廳 Windows 遊戲的交互方式
First step:
首先第一步
wake up Windows.
把 Windows 喚醒
In the past,
這要是在以前
you had to run over and press the power button.
你必須跑過去按一下開關
But the Steam Controller is different.
但 Steam 手柄不一樣
By default,
它默認狀態下
it is not recognized by the computer as a controller,
是不被電腦識別成手柄的
but as a keyboard and mouse.
而是鍵鼠
And when connected via the Puck,
而且通過 Puck 連接的時候
it is still a USB keyboard and mouse.
它還是 USB 鍵鼠
You can wake up the PC from the couch with the controller.
你可以坐在沙發上用手柄喚醒 PC
Isn't that great?
是不是很爽
When the computer first starts up,
電腦剛啟動的時候
the right touchpad is the mouse,
右觸控板是滑鼠
the left touchpad is the scroll wheel,
左觸控板是滾輪
the left trigger is right-click,
左扳機是右鍵
the right trigger is left-click,
右扳機是左鍵
A is Enter,
A 相當於回車
B is Escape,
B 相當於 Escape
the D-pad corresponds to the arrow keys on the keyboard.
上下左右就是鍵盤上的上下左右
At this point,
這個時候
we can perform simple operations
我們可以在 Windows 介面裏
in the Windows interface.
做一些簡單的操作
After that,
這之後
press the Steam button again
再按一下 Steam 鍵
to wake up Steam.
就會喚醒 Steam
When Steam is running,
Steam 運行的時候
the controller has more functions,
手柄就會有更多的功能
such as bringing up the virtual keyboard.
比如換出虛擬鍵盤
Press the Steam button again
再按一次 Steam 鍵
to enter Steam Big Picture mode,
就會進入 Steam 大屏版
an interface similar to the Steam Deck.
像 Steam Deck 一樣的介面
At this point,
這個時候呢
the controller enters normal console-style interaction.
手柄就會進入正常的主機式交互了
The touchpad's mission for UI interaction is thus complete.
觸控板交互 UI 的使命就此完成
If you still insist on using a mouse,
如果你還是非得用滑鼠的話
for example, when a software pop-up appears,
比如說有什麼軟體彈窗
you can still hold down this... key
那還是可以按住這個...鍵
to trigger the trackpad.
來觸發觸控板的
You can also do this:
還可以這樣
switch windows.
切換窗口
You can also use the trackpad to press the virtual keyboard.
也可以用觸控板來按虛擬鍵盤
Two fingers together is quite fast.
兩個手指一起還挺快的
Long press
長按
will show you various things you can trigger with the controller.
會顯示你能用手柄觸發的各種
Other shortcuts
其他快捷鍵
Quite a lot.
還挺多的
No need to get up during the entire operation.
全程操作不用起身
This is currently the closest Windows experience
這已經是目前最接近遊戲主機
to a plug-and-play game console.
即插即用的 Windows 體驗了
Once you enter the game,
進入遊戲以後
the trackpad performs similarly to the Steam Deck.
觸控板的表現就和 Steam Deck 上差不多
As you slide,
隨著滑動
there's motor vibration feedback underneath.
底下有馬達震動帶來回饋
Every area can also be pressed down.
每個地方也都可以按下去
You can play some
可以玩一些
strategy games designed specifically for keyboard and mouse.
專門為鍵鼠設計的策略遊戲
A colleague who prefers to remain anonymous said
我有一位不願意透露姓名的同事說
this trackpad is convenient for playing adult games.
這個觸控板用來玩很黃油方便
Oh, right, this trackpad
哦對了這個觸控板
is of course not just for use as a mouse.
當然不只是能夠用來當做滑鼠
It can also be configured as other buttons,
它還可以配置成其他的按鍵
like keyboard keys,
鍵盤上的按鍵
such as numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
比如數字 123456
for playing MMORPGs.
用來玩 MMORPG
It can even trigger specific in-game functions,
甚至可以觸發遊戲裏的特定功能
like in DOOM Eternal.
比如《DOOM Eternal》
Normally, switching weapons is a combination of buttons and joystick,
正常切換武器是組合按鍵加搖杆
but I can directly touch the trackpad
但是我可以直接觸摸觸控板
to trigger the weapon wheel.
觸發武器輪
Release to confirm.
鬆開確定
Let's talk about
正好我們就來說一下
the software that allows us to infinitely customize the Steam Controller,
允許我們無限自定義 Steam 手柄的軟體神器
Steam.
Steam
Yes,
對
it's Steam itself.
就是 Steam 本身
Because the Steam Controller
因為 Steam 手柄
is recognized as a special keyboard and mouse by default,
默認被識別成特殊的鍵鼠
you must open Steam
所以必須打開 Steam
for it to work like a controller.
它才能夠像手柄一樣工作
Steam itself is the driver for the controller.
Steam 本體就是手柄的驅動
Steam can display the controller's battery level,
Steam 能顯示手柄的電量
update firmware,
更新固件
show wireless signal strength,
顯示無線信號的強度
and even find the controller like a lost TV remote.
甚至像找不到電視遙控器一樣
You can call up your controller in Steam
你可以在 Steam 裏呼叫你的手柄
It feels like Valve forced everyone's Steam client
有種 Valve 強行給大家的 Steam 客戶端
to be stuffed with a lot of junk code
塞了好多垃圾代碼的感覺
You wouldn't need it if you don't buy a controller
不買手柄的話根本用不上
Just now I was talking about customization
剛剛說到自定義
I guess most people are like me
我猜大部分人和我一樣
It's too complicated
太複雜了
I'm so lazy
我好懶啊
I just use the defaults
我就乾脆用默認的唄
But actually, you don't need to study it much
但其實也不太需要去研究
Just use others'
直接用別人的
and that's it
就可以了
Because Steam Deck has sold nearly 8 million units
因為 Steam Deck 已經賣了快 800 萬臺
So for many popular games on Steam
所以 Steam 裏很多熱門遊戲
a lot of people have already uploaded
都已經有很多人上傳了
their own custom configuration files
自己做的自定義配置檔
They're in the community configurations of controller settings
就在手柄設置的社區配置裏
And as soon as the Steam Controller was born
而 Steam Controller 一出生
it could directly use these ready-made ones
就可以直接撿這些現成的用
For example
舉個例子
The Steam Controller and Steam Deck
Steam 手柄和 Steam Deck
like the Switch
Switch 一樣
both have gyroscope functionality
都有陀螺儀的功能
Allowing certain games to use the gyroscope
允許某些遊戲調用陀螺儀
for aiming in shooting games
來在射擊遊戲裏瞄準
Compensating for the lack of precision in joysticks
彌補了搖杆不夠精確的問題
The Splatoon series is like that
Splatoon 系列就是這樣的
Gyro aiming is actually great
陀螺儀瞄準其實很棒
Very close to the precision of a mouse
非常接近滑鼠的精確程度
And also very intuitive
也很符合直覺
But not many games support it
但支持的遊戲並不多
But that's okay
但沒關係
We can directly download
我們可以直接下載
gyroscope settings configured by others
別人配置好的陀螺儀設置
In Cyberpunk 2077
在《賽博朋克2077》裏
you can touch the touchpad
可以一觸摸觸控板
and the gyroscope will simulate mouse movement
陀螺儀就會模擬滑鼠移動
making aiming better
更好瞄準了
The Satisfactory mouse and keyboard configuration
《幸福工廠》模擬鍵鼠的配置
already has over a hundred thousand hours of playtime
已經有十幾萬小時的遊戲時長了
The grips on the back of the Steam Controller
Steam 手柄背後的握把
have additional touch sensor strips
額外增加了觸摸感應條
called Grip Sense
叫 Grip Sense
They can also be configured to trigger pause
還可以配置成觸發暫停
The degree of customization is very high
自定義程度非常高
Combined with the touchpad
配合著觸控板
I think the Steam Controller has solved
我覺得 Steam 手柄算是攻克了
most of the problems encountered when using a controller
大部分手柄來玩 PC 遊戲時
to play PC games
會遇到的難題了
Of course, all of this is based on
當然一切的前提是
All the games you want to play are on Steam.
你要玩的遊戲全部都在 Steam 上
The Steam Controller really can only be used with Steam.
Steam 手柄竟然真的只可以給 Steam 用
If Steam isn't running,
如果 Steam 沒有在運行
the controller isn't even recognized as a controller.
手柄根本不被識別成手柄
If you want to use it to play your Epic Games Store collection,
如果你想要用它玩你積攢的 Epic 商店
XGP, GOG,
XGP、GOG
or emulator games, pirated game resources,
或者模擬器遊戲 盜版遊戲資源
by default, it simply won't work.
默認是根本用不了的
Either you add them as non-Steam games,
要麼你就作為非 Steam 應用
one by one, into Steam,
一個一個添加到 Steam 裏
and launch them from Steam,
從 Steam 打開
or you download this open-source plugin called SISR,
要麼就下載這個叫做 SISR 的開源插件
and keep Steam running in the background.
同時在後臺打開著 Steam
Either way, it's quite a hassle.
其實都挺麻煩的
Not to mention,
更不要說
it can't be used with any game console either.
它也沒有辦法給任何遊戲主機使用
This compatibility, combined with its $100 price tag,
這個相容性加上 700 元的定價
makes it really hard to recommend to everyone.
讓它真的很不容易推薦給所有人
For $100, you can buy a PS5 controller,
700 塊能買一個 PS5 手柄
plus an extra Xbox controller,
再額外加一個 Xbox 手柄
or several third-party controllers.
第三方手柄能買好幾個
And compared to the PS5 controller,
何況跟 PS5 手柄比
it doesn't even have adaptive triggers.
它還沒有自適應扳機
It's not a total win, you know.
還不是全面碾壓哦
If you just need a controller to pair with keyboard and mouse
如果你只是需要一個和鍵鼠配合的
for playing AAA games,
玩 3A 遊戲用的遊戲手柄
you might as well look at third-party controllers.
那還不如去看一看第三方手柄呢
But if you want a gaming PC to replace a console
但如果你希望讓一臺遊戲 PC 取代主機
and become the center of your living room gaming,
成為客廳遊戲的中心
without the hassle of keyboard and mouse,
又不想搞很麻煩的鍵鼠
then besides the Steam Controller,
那除了 Steam 手柄
you really have no other choice.
你還真的沒有任何其他的選擇
I think the $100 price tag
我覺得 700 塊的定價
for this Steam Controller
對於這個 Steam Controller 來說
is right at
算是剛好踩在了
the tipping point of value for money.
那個性價比的臨界線上
Any more expensive and it would be a bit of a rip-off.
再貴一點就有一點坑了
Only those who truly
只有真的
need its unique features
非常需要它的這些獨特性的人
will feel it's worth the buy.
才會覺得買的很值
But then again,
但話又說回來
the Steam Controller
Steam 手柄
was never meant
本來就不需要
to be a standalone product.
成為一個獨當一面的產品
It was supposed to be bundled with the Steam Machine.
它是要配合 Steam Machine 打包上市的
It was only because of the memory crisis
只是因為記憶體危機
that the controller was released first.
手柄才先放出來了
And yet, just a controller
結果一個手柄
can bring so many changes
就可以讓客廳 PC 遊戲體驗
to the living room PC gaming experience.
有這麼多的變化
It makes you look forward even more
就讓人更想期待
to the Steam Machine that follows
之後的 Steam Machine 了